דף *Daf* we are doing today is ע"א *Ayin Aleph* 71 and
we pick up at the top, two lines from the top, and
we're making our way through this fascinating משנה Mishnah *mishna*. So the
first part of the משנה Mishnah *mishna* had to do with two
witnesses saying it was stolen, it was burgled, and she's saying it
was slaughtered, which led to this question about דבר וחצי דבר *davar
v'chatzi davar*, when a witness has to testify to a whole thing
or can a witness testify to a part of a thing. Then
it dealt with selling on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*, that there was no
concept of קים ליה Kimlei *Kimlei* because שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* is violated
in the act of selling, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* constructed a
scenario where שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos* would be violated in the act of
selling, and it says in that case you would not be liable
for four and five because you would say קים ליה Kimlei *Kimlei*,
so you wouldn't have the punishment of four and five. But then
it led to the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s interesting question: would the principle
of קים ליה Kimlei *Kimlei* void the sale or not? And it
basically concluded, well, the קים ליה Kimlei. *Kimlei* might prevent us from
enforcing the sale, but it wouldn't void the sale to the point
that there's a sense of חייב chayav בידי שמים *chayav bidei shamayim*
if the person actually went through with the transaction, would have been
considered to be based on the sale and therefore it would be
a sale that you'd be liable for four and five. So that
was a fascinating discussion about the idea of קים ליה Kimlei? *Kimlei*
voiding some type of an interpersonal transaction, a sale, we discussed a
contract and so on. Now we move on to the next part
of the משנה Mishnah *mishna*, which has another case that you pay
four and five, which is somebody stole it and slaughtered it on
יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur*. So the slaughtering an animal on
יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur* is a violation of יום כיפור
Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur*, you're חייב chayav כרת *chayav kares*, but it's
assuming that you're not going to say קים ליה Kimlei *Kimlei* because
it's not liable the death penalty. So this is the issue that
the גמרא gemara *Gemara* turns to. So two lines from the top,
גנב ganav ומכר ביום הכיפורים *ganav u'machar b'Yom haKippurim*. אמרי amri, *Amrei*,
so you should say אמאי *Amai*, why is it that he's exempt
from... I mean, why is it that he pays four and five,
that we don't say the principle of קים ליה Kimlei, *Kimlei* when
an animal is slaughtered on יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*? הי
דקטלא ליכא *He d'katala leka*, admittedly you're not liable the death penalty,
מלקות malkus. מי איכא *malkus mi ika*, you are liable lashes. Anytime
that you're חייב chayav כרת *chayav kares*, if you have a warning
regarding lashes, then the lashes... then you would get lashes. So for
a violation of יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur* you could get
lashes, and we should normally say קיימא לן דאינו לוקה ומשלם lokeh
um'shaleim. *kaim lan d'eino loke v'mishalen*, you don't get lashes and pay.
Now there's a lot of interesting places the גמרא gemara *Gemara* could
go here. First of all, it's interesting the גמרא gemara *Gemara* had
to go to the lashes discussion. Why didn't it say that כרת
*kares* is enough of a principle to override payment? Would you say
a principle of קים ליה Kimlei, *Kimlei* for a divine punishment that
is not executed by the courts? Right, that's an interesting question. It's
a slightly different question than if somebody is חייב מיתה chayav misa,
*chayav misa* but there's no witnesses. Right, there at least it's a
type of a sin that would be punished by the courts, but
the circumstances are such that the court cannot do the punishment. A
type of a sin that would never be punished by the court,
even if it's very weighty, כרת *kares*, that's an interesting question, would
you say קים ליה kim lei *Kimlei* by that? The other thing
the גמרא gemara *Gemara* could have gone to, since it felt it
had to go to the מלקות malkus. *malkus* route, is to say,
well, maybe it's only when the person was actually warned about מלקות
*malkus* and is going to get מלקות *malkus*. This is an issue
that we've discussed before, that when it's a sin that you're liable
the death penalty, right, that's תנא דבי חזקיה *Tana d'vei Chizkiyah* is
that it doesn't matter if you did it במזיד b'meizid, *b'meizid*, בשוגג
beshogeg, *b'shogeg*, with witnesses, without witnesses, if it's such a weighty sin
that you get the death penalty, it overrides, you say קים ליה
kim lei. *Kimlei*, it overrides other types of
payment. Yes, and what kind of punishment would be
if
there was no
witness? From no witnesses, how could
they...
There wouldn't be a punishment, but it would be a sin deserving
of a punishment. So by case where it's a sin deserving of
the death penalty, even if there were no witnesses and no warning
and even if it was בשוגג beshogeg *b'shogeg*, we would say it
would override monetary payment. But when it comes to מלקות *malkus*, we
normally say it's only when the punishment is going to be administered.
So if the גמרא gemara *Gemara* is saying, well, why when you
slaughtered on יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur* did it not override
the payment of four and five, one easy place the גמרא gemara
*Gemara* could have gone could have said, well, maybe it's a scenario
that there was no warning or witnesses and so on, and we're
not administering the מלקות *malkus*. Okay, and תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* basically makes
that point. But the גמרא gemara *Gemara* isn't going to say that.
Okay, maybe it could have, but let's see where the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* does go. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says, how come you're
going to... you're not going to say קים ליה kim lei. *Kimlei*
in this יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur* case? So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, הא מני רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, היא *Ha mani
Rabbi Meir hi*, this is going according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir,
*Rabbi Meir*, דאמר d'amar לוקה ומשלם *d'amar loke v'mishalen*, we know there's
a רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, *Rabbi Meir* position in מכות *Makkot* that
says you can get lashes and pay. It's a case about עדים
זוממין *eidim zomemin* where רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says they'll
both get lashes for violating לא lo. תענה ברעך עד שקר *lo
sa'ane b'reiacha ed shaker*, testifying falsely, and they will pay if they
testified about somebody owing money. So they'll do the payment of עדים
זוממין *eidim zomemin*. and get lashes. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's
possible to get both. And that's why on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur
the guy will still pay four and five. רב אשי Rav Ashi
says one minute. אי רבי מאיר, Ei Rabbi Meir, if it's רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir אפילו טבח בשבת, afillu tavach b'Shabbos, maybe רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir if he's going to say you don't say קים ליה
kim lei. by lashes, maybe he'll say you don't say קים ליה
kim lei. even by a חייב מיתה, chayav misa, a sin deserving
of the death penalty. And we know that our משנה Mishnah says
on יום כיפור Yom Kippur you pay four and five, but on
שבת Shabbos. where there's a קים ליה Kimle, principle of חייב מיתה,
chayav misa if you slaughtered the animal, the later משנה Mishnah is
going to say you're exempt from paying four and five. But if
it's רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir maybe you should never say קים ליה.
Kimle וכי תימא, V'chi teima, now let's say you're going to say,
like we just said before, there's a huge difference between חייב מיתה
chayav misa, and מלקות. What?
How do you get from that that the משנה Mishnah says not
saying קים ליה? Kimle.
Well, that's what the גמרא's Gemara, going to say. Okay, וכי תימא,
v'chi teima, if you're going to say, לאו כדמשנינן השתא, lav k'demashninan
hashta, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir holds you get lashes and pay, מיתה
ומשלמין לאו איכא, misa u'meshalmin lav ika, getting the death penalty, that's
a completely different category, like we just mentioned a little while ago.
So maybe what allows you to say that for רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir. you would get the death penalty and pay? No, it could
work. In our משנה Mishnah. you get lashes and pay, but if
it's a חילול שבת, chillul Shabbos, you wouldn't actually get the death
penalty and pay and then you would be exempt from four and
five. Okay, that's a logical distinction, but I'm going to show you
a ברייתא braisa that indicates that according to רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
you could get the death penalty and still pay four and five.
והתניא, V'ha tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braisa, ולאו דקתני, v'lo
d'katani, is that not the case? והתניא, V'ha tanya, we taught in
the ברייתא, braisa, גנב וטבח בשבת גנב וטבח לעבודה זרה, ganav v'tavach
b'Shabbos ganav v'tavach l'avoda zara, somebody stole and slaughtered it on שבת
Shabbos or stole and slaughtered it to עבודה זרה, avoda zara, two
things that you're חייב מיתה, chayav missa, liable the death penalty. גנב
שור הנסקל וטבחו, Ganav shor haniskal v'tavacho, or stole a שור הנסקל
shor haniskal and slaughtered it, which is fascinating because presumably a שור
הנסקל shor haniskal is not worth anything, but we'll get to שור
הנסקל shor haniskal in a minute. משלם ארבעה וחמשה, Meshaleim arba v'chamisha,
you pay four and
five. דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi Meir, that's what רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir, says. So you see you're paying four and five even though
you're liable the death penalty. So presumably it sounds like רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir doesn't hold of קים ליה Kimle, at all. So our
משנה mishna can't be going like רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir because our
משנה mishna. holds of it by שבת, shabbos just not by יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur? So you're back to having the problem with the
משנה. mishna: וחכמים פוטרין, Vachachamim potrin, but the Sages exempt you. They
exempt you on the first two cases because of a קים ליה,
Kimle, and on the שור הנסקל shor haniskal we'll see, but the
most obvious reason is a שור הנסקל shor haniskal isn't worth anything.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, אמרי, amri, you can say,
okay, so now we've got to deal with this רבי מאיר. Rebbi
Meir So אמרי, Amri, you could say בר מיניה דהא, bar minei
d'ha, no no no, that ברייתא, braisa, put that ברייתא braisa aside,
bracket that ברייתא. braisa. Okay, why? Because that's not really a principle
that you can get the death penalty and pay. There's a different
thing going on in that ברייתא. braisa. What's going on in that
ברייתא? braisa? הא
איתמר עלה,
Ha
itmar
alah, it was said about it, אמר רבי יעקב אמר רבי יוחנן
ואמרי לה אמר רבי ירמיה אמר רבי שמעון בן
לקיש רבי אבין ורבי אילא וכל חברותא,
Amar Rabbi Yaakov Amar Rabbi Yochanan v'amri lah Amar Rabbi Yirmiyah Amar
Rabbi
Shimon ben Lakish Rabbi Avin v'Rabbi Ila v'chol chavrusah, so there's a
tradition of people who reported that these other group of rabbis, רבי
אבין Rabbi Avin and רבי אילא Rabbi Ila and the whole sort
of a community of rabbis, the whole בית מדרש, beis medrash, משמיה
דרבי יוחנן, mishmeih d'Rabbi Yochanan, they all explained this ברייתא braisa in
the name of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Wait, רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan
reporting in his own name?
משמיה דרבי יוחנן. Mishmeih d'Rabbi Yochanan.
Oh you're right, maybe it's the first was just אמר רבי יעקב
אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yaakov Amar Rabbi Yochanan and then the
second was אמר רבי ירמיה אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש רבי אבין
ורבי אילא וכל חברותא משמיה דרבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Yirmiyah Amar Rabbi
Shimon ben Lakish Rabbi Avin v'Rabbi Ila v'chol chavrusah mishmeih d'Rabbi Yochanan.
You're probably right. Okay, good catch. Anyway, רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan
one group and רבי ריש לקיש. Rabbi Reish Lakish.
Right,
that's true, but okay, fine, either רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says directly
or this whole group says in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, one way or the other, anyway, what are we going to
do with this crazy ברייתא braisa that says that you pay four
and five in a case of a death penalty? So no no,
it's got to be talking about something else. אמרי, amri, it's talking
about the following case. בטובח על ידי אחר, B'toveach al yedei acher,
somebody else got, Reuven stole it or burgled it, gave it to
Shimon and said, Shimon, turn you know, he brought it to Shimon
the butcher and he said, Shimon, I want some meat, here's my
cow. Okay, Shimon didn't know any better, he thought it was Reuven's
cow, he slaughtered it. Okay, and but you know Shimon wasn't a
שומר שבת shomer Shabbos guy. So Shimon slaughtered it on שבת. shabbos.
Okay, so it was slaughtered on שבת shabbos. but Reuven is going
to pay four and five because Reuven was the גנב ganav and
Reuven wasn't the one who was מחלל שבת. mechallel Shabbos. Okay, that's
all very nice why we're not going to say קים ליה, Kimle.
but the obvious question is why is Reuven going to pay four
and five? He wasn't the one who slaughtered. The תורה Torah says
if you burgled it and you sold it, or you burgled it
and you slaughtered it, not if you burgled it and gave it
to your butcher and had your butcher slaughter it. So that's going
to be the next חידוש. chiddush. So let's take a look. וכי
זה חוטא וזה מתחייב? V'chi zeh chotei v'zeh mischayeiv? Can this one
sin and this one become liable? How can Shimon slaughter it and
Reuven pay four and five? So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, no, שאני
הכא דאמר קרא, shani hacha d'amar kra, here it is possible because
the פסוק pasuk says
וטבחו ומכרו u'tovacho u'mechoro and you slaughtered it or you sold it.
So מה מכירה על ידי אחר, ma mechira al yedei acher, the
same way you can't sell something without two people, you need a
buyer, so אף טביחה על ידי אחר, af tvicha al yedei acher,
when you slaughter it it could also be with another person involved,
it could be through a butcher, through somebody else even if you
don't do it personally. Now this is a very big חידוש. chiddush.
First of all one wonders what if you sold it through an
agent? Like could you have two אחר acher operating by the selling
or is it just by the slaughtering? But the basic point though
is Is that, look, you as the גנב *ganav*, remember, why you
paying four and five when you sold it and slaughtered it? Is
it such a big עבירה *aveirah*? I mean you've already stolen the
object. Right, exactly, you've already stolen the object from the owner, so,
you know, it's not like, I mean, why is slaughtering somebody's animal
a sin that's worth four and five times? I mean, so, the
point is as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said before, no, it just
shows how much you are repeating your sin or setting roots into
נשתנה בחטא או נשתרש בחטא *nishtana be-cheita o nishtarish be-cheita*, how much
you're entrenching your sin. So the point could be there at that
stage, it's not so much a question whether you did it personally
or not. The fact that even you caused it to be done,
right, was a furthering of what you did. You stole it and
you got it even further away from the owners, okay? So maybe
because it focuses the actual sin was the original sin, this is
just putting roots into it, you know, or just, you know, underscoring
it. So maybe it's not so critical you're the one that does
it, it's enough that you had it done. Now, if somebody came
along and slaughtered your animal without your permission, obviously you would not
be חייב chayav *chayav*. But you don't have to do it personally,
it's just that you had it done, okay, which in a certain
way also makes sense. Like, is everybody a שוחט shechting *shochet*? So,
you know, I mean, what do we think when the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says if you steal it and slaughter it? Do we really
think it means that you happen to be a שוחט shechting *shochet*?
I mean, it's a pretty reasonable point that included in that would
mean I stole it and I got my butcher to slaughter it.
Well right, that's a question by סמיכה *smicha*. So what? What? Well,
that's exactly what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, וכי חוטא זה מתחייב
*v'chi chotei zeh mitchayev*? But the answer is, yes, the answer is
שאני הכא *shani hacha*, that even if there's no שליח shaliach. לדבר
עבירה *shaliach l'dvar aveirah*, here the תורה Torah *Torah* says this is
the way in which you are חייב chayav. *chayav*, whether you do
it personally or whether you have someone do it for you. Okay,
that's exactly right I think what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s answer is.
I mean the butcher
is חייב chayav
*chayav* for חילול שבת chillul shabbos *chilul Shabbat*.
Right, he's still חייב chayav *chayav* for חילול שבת chillul shabbos. *chilul
Shabbat*, but the point is it's not the sin of slaughtering you
pay four and five, it's the sin of נשתנה או נשתרש בחטא
*nishtana o nishtarish be-cheita* through slaughtering and selling, and that can be
even through having somebody do it for you. Okay, so that's the
big חידוש chiddush *chiddush* here. All right, so now we- so now
it makes sense. This ברייתא braita *braita* that רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir
*Rabbi Meir* says you pay four and five even on שבת shabbos?
*Shabbat* is a some- also thank you, is that somebody else was
doing it for you. Okay, and that's why it has nothing to
do, of course, why didn't you just say that? Say if you
have somebody else do it for you. All right, whatever. But we're
going to bracket that idea. Nobody's going to say you're going to
be מחלל שבת mechalel shabbos, *mechalel Shabbat* personally and pay four and
five. And now the ברייתא braita *braita* that says that if you
do it on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, you pay four and five,
that's רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir, *Rabbi Meir*'s position, that he would say
you get lashes and you can pay, you won't get מיתה misa.
*misah* and pay, but you can get lashes and pay. All right,
so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
What happens if the agent also was aware that this is a
crime that?
Oh,
that wouldn't change things. I mean, how should it change things? You
mean that then you should say that you shouldn't be חייב chayav
*chayav* four and five because he shouldn't have done it at all?
I was just curious if they were both- No,
presumably that won't change anything. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this. דבי רבי ישמעאל
תנא
*de-bei Rabbi Yishmael tana*, the house of רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* we
taught, או *o* לרבות את השליח *l'rabot et ha-shaliach*, another way to
get that you can even if you sell it or slaughter it
through another person, not by the linking to selling but by the
word או *o*. It could have said וטבחו ve-tavacho, ומכרו *u-tevacho u-mechoro*
and it says או מכרו *o mechoro* means even in some other
fashion, I don't know exactly how we get that. Okay. דבי חזקיה
תנא *de-bei Chizkiyah tana*, תחת *tachat* לרבות את השליח *l'rabot et ha-shaliach*.
ארבע צאן תחת השה *arba tzon tachat ha-seh*, חמישה-
what is it? חמישה בקר תחת השור *chamisha bakar tachat ha-shor*, ארבע
צאן תחת השה *arba
tzon tachat ha-seh*,
thank you. Okay, so the תחת *tachat* somehow means maybe somebody acting
תחת *tachat* you, in your stead. I don't get- exactly get it,
but somehow there was a sense, you know, it seems like they
started with this understanding that even if you did it through someone
else and we found different ways to דרשן *darshen* it. Okay. מתקי
לה מר זוטרא *matki lei Mar Zutra*, so מר זוטרא *Mar Zutra*
asked, מי איכא מידי *mi ikha midi*? One minute, one minute, says
מר זוטרא *Mar Zutra*, I don't get it. The butcher did it
on שבת shabbos. *Shabbat*, you're going to pay four and five. So,
one minute, מי איכא מידי *mi ikha midi*, do we have a
case that דאי עביד איהו לא מיחייב *d'ee avid ihu lo michayav*,
had you been the one to do it on שבת shabbos *Shabbat*,
you wouldn't pay because we would say קם ליה *kam lei*, דעביד
שליח מיחייב *d'avid shaliach michayav*? So even if you say that if
somebody does it for you you're חייב chayav? *chayav*, how can they
be more חייב chayav. *chayav* than you would have been had you
been done it personally? So if you did it personally you'd be
exempt because of שבת shabbos, *Shabbat*, how can their doing it make
you חייב chayav. *chayav*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, and what
I think is an obvious answer, אמר ליה רב Amar lei Rav,
אשי *amar lei Rav Ashi*, התם לאו משום דלא מיחייב הוא *hatam
lav mishum d'lo michayav hu*, if you would have done it personally,
it's not because fundamentally that would not have been something that would
have created a liability a four and five, your slaughtering it fundamentally
would be an act that would have block- made you liable four
and five, אלא דקם ליה בדרבה מיניה *ela de-kam lei b'draba minei*,
there would have been some other thing which would have, which would
have voided it. Okay, so but fundamentally you as the גנב *ganav*
if you slaughter it you're חייב chayav *chayav* four and five. If
you do it in certain circumstances you're going to avoid the payment,
but that doesn't mean that somebody else, you know, if they can
do it for you and be חייב hayav. *chayav* four and five
just like you would have been חייב hayav *chayav* four and five
and then it's just the circumstance. The avoiding doesn't take place because
you're not being מחלל שבת mechalel shabbos. at that moment. Okay, now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, fine. So we've got it. The
ברייתא braita. that says you pay four and five when you do
it on שבת shabbos, is because you did it through a שליח.
ר' מאיר Rebbi Meir still holds that a normal case of חילול
שבת chillul shabbos. you wouldn't pay four and five. The משנה Mishnah.
that says you pay four and five on יום כיפור is ר'
מאיר, Rebbi Meir, but ר' מאיר Rebbi Meir says for lashes you
will pay four and five, not for מיתה. And again, the ברייתא
braita is talking about a case that you did it through somebody
else. So now we've somewhat explained the משנה. Mishnah Let's go back
and explain this ברייתא. braita What is the, why are the חכמים
chachamim debating ר' מאיר? Rebbi Meir? If we're talking that you did
it through an agent and you did it on שבת. shabbos, Now
the easiest thing to be today would be maybe the חכמים chachamim
don't hold of this idea. Maybe they hold that if you did
it through another person, you're exempt. Has nothing to do with שבת.
shabbos Okay, but the גמרא Gemara now that it's introduced this idea
that you're חייב hayav four and five through another person wants to
assume that that's agreed between ר' מאיר Rebbi Meir and the חכמים.
chachamim. So then why do the חכמים chachamim say you're exempt? So
let's take a look. ואי בטובח על ידי אחר, ve-ee b'tove'ach al
yedei acher, if you're doing it through another party and this and
you could be חייב hayav. four and five through another party,
so מאי טעמא דרבנן דפטרי, mai ta'ama d'rabbanan d'pattri, why do the
רבנן rabbanan exempt you? So what if it's done on שבת? shabbos.
Big deal it's done on שבת. shabbos. You wasn't מחלל שבת, shabbos
the butcher was מחלל שבת. shabbos. And if you could be חייב
hayav. through the butcher, why are you, why you would be exempt?
אמרי מאן חכמים ר' שמעון. amri man chachamim Rebbi Shimon. Who are
the חכמים chachamim here that exempt you? It's ר' שמעון. Rebbi Shimon.
דאמר שחיטה שאינה ראויה לא שמה שחיטה. de'amar shechita she'eina re'uya lo
shema shechita. Now there actually is a nice answer. It sounds like
a little bit of a קוועטש kvetch because you went from שבת
shabbos to שחיטה שאינה ראויה, shechita she'eina re'uya, but you remember the
ברייתא Braitza talked about three
scenarios: slaughtering it on
שבת, Shabbos slaughtering it to עבודה זרה, avoda zara, and slaughtering a
שור הנסקל. shor haniskal. So the first two sound like a קים
ליה Kimle issue. The third sounds like something else. So what the
גמרא Gemara has actually said is it's made all three being the
same thing. All three of them is a slaughtering that doesn't make
the meat permissible. It has nothing to do with חילול שבת. chillul
shabbos It has nothing to do with קים ליה. Kimle It has
to do with the fact when you שחט shacht something to עבודה
זרה, avoda zara, you make it a תקרובת עבודה זרה, tikroves avoda
zara, something offered to עבודה זרה avoda zara which is forbidden in
הנאה. hana'ah. When you שחט shacht a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, you
can't eat it. Now when you שחט shacht something on שבת, Shabbos
we're about to look at, there's also a principle you can't benefit
from a חילול שבת. chillul shabbos. So the גמרא Gemara is actually
saying, alright, so we'll see about that. But the גמרא Gemara is
saying now a very nice elegant answer. Don't get distracted with the
חילול שבת chillul Shabbos here with the whatever. This is not about
קים ליה. Kimle Forget קים ליה. kimle? Somebody else did it. The
butcher did it. Okay, it's not about קים ליה. kimle This whole
ברייתא Braitza is about the fact that when you slaughtered it, you
didn't make the meat fit to be eaten. And ר' מאיר Rebbi
Meir says I don't care, it's still an act of slaughtering. And
the חכמים chachamim say like ר' שמעון: Rebbi Shimon: שחיטה שאינה ראויה
לא שמה שחיטה. shechita she'eina re'uya lo shema shechita. If it did
not make it fit to be eaten, you're not liable. Okay, now
let's look at these scenarios. So let's take a look.
The גמרא Gemara says like this:
אמרי בשלמא עבודה זרה. amri bishlama avoda zara. The גמרא Gemara says
look, I get it, it works for
עבודה זרה ושור הנסקל. avodah zarah v'shor haniskal. השחיטה שאינה ראויה היא.
hashechita she'eina re'uya hee. The שחיטה shechita is not fit, it doesn't
make the meat fit to be eaten. אלא שבת שחיטה ראויה היא.
ela shabbos shechita re'uya hee. But by שבת, Shabbos. the meat can
be eaten. דתנן, detnan, we taught in the
משנה: Mishnah. השוחט בשבת, hashochet b'shabbos, exactly case of שחיטה, shechita, you
שחט shacht on שבת Shabbos, וביום הכיפורים, ub'yom hakippurim, אף על פי
שמתחייב בנפשו, af al pi shemitchayev b'nafsho, although you're liable the death
penalty, שחיטה כשרה, shechita kesheira, the שחיטה shechita is still כשרה, kesheira,
the meat is כשר kosher to be eaten. So therefore, how do
you make it a case of שחיטה שאינה ראויה? shechita she'eina re'uya?
So אמרי, you could say, סבר לה כר' יוחנן הסנדלר, savar lah
k'Rebbi Yochanan HaSandlar, he's like ר' יוחנן הסנדלר. Rebbi Yochanan HaSandlar. דתנן:
detnan: המבשל בשבת, hamevashel b'shabbos, let's do another case of חילול שבת.
chilul Shabbat? Somebody cooks on שבת. Shabbos. בשוגג יאכל, beshogeg yochel, if
it's an unintentional violation, he can eat it. Even he himself can
eat it. And רש"י Rashi says even on the day itself. There's
a whole debate of the ראשונים rishonim because not all the parameters
are spelled out here. But we'll read it like רש"י. Rashi. Even
the person himself can eat it בשוגג, beshogeg, even on the day
itself. במזיד לא יאכל, b'meizid lo yochel, דברי ר' מאיר. divrei Rebbi
Meir. But if it was במזיד, b'meizid, then he nor, רש"י Rashi
says, anybody can eat it on the day itself. Afterwards you can
eat it, but on the day itself it can't be eaten.
That's what ר' מאיר Rebbi Meir says. Okay, so whether בשוגג b'shogeg
or במזיד, b'meizid, whatever, that would be limited to the question of
eating it on the day itself according to ר' מאיר. Rebbi Meir.
ר' יהודה אומר בשוגג יאכל במוצאי שבת. Rebbi Yehuda omer beshogeg yochel
b'motzei shabbos. If it was בשוגג, you or other people, again according
to רש"י, Rashi, could eat it after שבת. Shabbos Nobody can eat
it on שבת Shabbos itself, but it can be eaten after שבת.
Shabbos במזיד, b'meizid, if it was במזיד, b'meizid לא יאכל לעולם. lo
yochel l'olamis. You, the violator, can never eat it. Other people can,
but you can't. Okay, so ר' יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, again, he says
he extends it for the במזיד BeMezid, guy, he extends it to
apply it would apply even after שבת Shabbos, for the violator and
it would apply forever. All right, but that still would not make
it a שחיטה שאינה ראויה shechita she'eina re'uya because other people could
eat from it.
ר' יוחנן הסנדלר אומר, Rebbi Yochanan HaSandlar omer, now here's where we
get it to be
a שחיטה שאינה ראויה. shechita she'eina re'uya. בשוגג יאכל beshogeg yochel Only
after שבת Shabbos, can it be eaten and only by other people.
On שבת Shabbos nobody can eat from it. Okay, so שוגג Shogeg
is still a שחיטה ראויה Shechita Reuyah for רבי יוחנן הסנדלר. Rebbi
Yochanan HaSandlar. At least other people can eat it after שבת. Shabbos
But במזיד, BeMezid, if it's a willful violation, לא לו
ולא. lo lo velo. במזיד, b'meizid לא יאכל עולמית לא לו ולא
לאחרים. lo ye'achel olamis, lo lo velo l'acherim. Nobody can ever eat
from it, not the violator, nobody else. For רבי יוחנן הסנדלר Rebbi
Yochanan HaSandlar you have a scenario of a שחיטה שאינה ראויה Shechita
Sheina Reuyah which was done intentionally, nobody can eat from it. So
that would be how this would work and they would all be
cases of שחיטה שאינה ראויה. Shechita Sheina Reuyah. One minute. So the
גמרא Gemara, says, מאי טעמא דרבי יוחנן הסנדלר? Mai ta'ama de'Rebbi Yochanan
HaSandlar? What's his reasoning? כידרש רבי חייא פתחא דבי נשיאה Kidarsh Rebbi
Chiya Pitcha de'Bei Nesi'ah like רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya expounded by the
doorstep of the house of the נשיא, Nasi, ושמרתם את השבת, U'shmartem
es haShabbos, you shall observe the שבת, Shabbos כי קודש היא לכם,
ki kodesh hi lachem, it is holy to you. So מה קודש
אסור באכילה, ma kodesh assur ba'achilah, the same way sanctified things are
forbidden to be eaten, אף מעשה שבת אסור באכילה, af ma'aseh Shabbos
assur ba'achilah, even things that are done on שבת. Shabbos. So שבת
Shabbos is sanctified, somehow that means that not only the day of
שבת Shabbos is sanctified, but a violation of שבת Shabbos somehow sanctifies
the food or makes the food off-limits. Okay, it's an interesting דרשה.
drasha. So אי מה קודש אסור בהנאה, i ma kodesh assur ba'hana'ah,
let's take the דרשה drasha to the fullest extent, you're not allowed
even get benefit from anything that's קודש. kodesh. אף מעשה שבת אסור
בהנאה, af ma'aseh Shabbos assur ba'hana'ah, let's say you can't even get
benefit, why does it say don't eat the food? Okay, presumably it's
only forbidden to be eaten, okay, but you can give it to
your dog, why does it, presumably you can get benefit, why don't
we treat it like full קודש kodesh and say you can't get
any benefit? תלמוד לומר לכם, Talmud lomar lachem, כי קודש היא לכם,
ki kodesh hi lachem, but it still remains yours to some degree.
שלכם יהא. Shelachem yehei. So you can get some benefit, but it
has, at least it's off, at least you can't eat it. יכול
אפילו בשוגג? Yachol afilu b'shogeg? Now, maybe I should say even on
שוגג shogeg these laws should apply and you shouldn't be able to
benefit from it. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, מחלליה מות יומת. mechaleleha mos
yumas. The end of that פסוק pasuk is, right, those who violate
it will be put to death. במזיד אמרתי לך B'mezid amarti lacha
this context is willful violation and ולא בשוגג, lo b'shogeg, not unintentional.
Okay, so now if you do חילול שבת chilul Shabbat... בשוגג it's
not קודש? kodesh?
Well, it's also a מחלליה mechaleleha that's מות יומת, mos yumas, so
clearly we're dealing about willful violation. So anyway, so the גמרא, Gemara
so רבי יוחנן הסנדלר Rebbi Yochanan HaSandlar the גמרא Gemara assumes that
of course רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir and רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda who
say differences between you and others on שבת, Shabbos, after שבת, Shabbos,
that's all like a דרבנן deRabbanan קנס knas or a disincentive for
violation of שבת Shabbos. if you know you won't be able to
benefit from it. But רבי יוחנן הסנדלר Rebbi Yochanan HaSandlar seems to
learn it out as a דאורייתא deOraisa and seems to say that
no, that it's completely becomes דאורייתא deOraisa forbidden to be eaten, which
gets to another גמרא, Gemara an interesting discussion. Should we learn from
here or should this be seen as an application of a more
general principle that any violation of a of a prohibition the produce
of that violation would become forbidden to be eaten? Like we know
that's not true, right, like you can make cross, you can cross-breed
fruit and eat the fruit, right? That's like a what are tangelos
and whatever, you know, that's a could be a violation of כלאיים.
kilayim. So but nevertheless there are times when a violation, the produce
of the violation is forbidden, and here we have a specific פסוק,
pasuk, so the גמרא Gemara says for רבי יוחנן הסנדלר Rebbi Yochanan
HaSandlar it's שחיטה שאינה ראויה shechita sheina reuyah and that's the debate
that's going on. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, we're not
done
yet. פליגי בה רב
אחא ורבינא. Pligi bah Rav Acha veRavina. Now, the position of רבי
יוחנן הסנדלר Rebbi Yochanan HaSandlar the scope is a debate or not
the scope the weight is a debate of רב אחא ורבינא. Rav
Acha veRavina. חד אמר מעשה שבת דאורייתא, Chad amar ma'aseh Shabbos deOraisa,
it's biblical and this דרשה drasha is a real דרשה. drasha. וחד
אמר מעשה שבת דרבנן, veChad amar ma'aseh Shabbos deRabbanan, no it's דרבנן
deRabbanan it's only an אסמכתא asmachtah even for רבי יוחנן הסנדלר. Rebbi
Yochanan HaSandlar. So מאן דאמר דאורייתא כי דאמרינן, man de'amar deOraisa kide'amran,
so if it's דאורייתא deOraisa it works, because then it's a real
שחיטה שאינה ראויה shechita sheina reuyah on a תורה Torah level, whether
it's עבודה זרה, avoda zara whether it's שור הנסקל shor haniskal or
whether it is שבת Shabbos, according to רבי יוחנן הסנדלר Rebbi Yochanan
HaSandlar and that's why you would not be liable according to רבי
מאיר, Rebbe Meir excuse me, according to the רבנן. Rabbanan. מאן דאמר
דרבנן, man de'amar deRabbanan, but the one that says it's דרבנן, deRabbanan,
אמאי פטרי רבנן? amai patari Rabbanan? What does he do with the
פסוק? pasuk? אמר קרא, Amar kra, קודש היא, kodesh hi, היא קודש
ואין מעשיה קודש. Hi kodesh ve'ein ma'aseha kodesh. He says the opposite,
only שבת Shabbos is קודש, kodesh, not the things that were created
as a produce of שבת. Shabbos, So good, so בשלמא למאן דאמר
דאורייתא, bishlama leman de'amar deOraisa, if it's דאורייתא deOraisa אמטו להכי, amtu
lehachi, once you have come with that position פטר להכי patar lehachi
פטרי רבנן. patari Rabbanan. Now we understand what the debate is. It's
a שחיטה שאינה ראויה, shechita sheina reuyah, רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir isn't
bothered by that he says you're liable for four and five, the
רבנן Rabbanan say you're exempt. They say whether it's עבודה זרה, avodah
zarah, שור הנסקל shor haniskal or שבת Shabbos all these things are
biblically you can't eat from them, at least שבת Shabbos according to
רבי יוחנן הסנדלר, Rebbi Yochanan HaSandlar, and therefore you're not חייב hayav
for four and five. אלא למאן דאמר דרבנן, Ella leman de'amar deRabbanan,
but the one that says that even according to רבי יוחנן הסנדלר
Rebbi Yochanan HaSandlar it's only rabbinically forbidden, אמאי פטרי רבנן? amai patari
Rabbanan? Why do the rabbis say you're exempt from four and five,
is שבת Shabbos, fit to be eaten? So the גמרא's Gemara answer
is אשארה, ashara, עבודה זרה avodah zarah, ושור הנסקל. v'shor haniskal. Fine,
when they say you're exempt they don't mean on every single thing
that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said you're
liable for three things, שבת, Shabbos עבודה זרה avodah zarah and שור
הנסקל, shor haniskal, and רב Rab You're פטור, patur, but they meant
you're פטור patur on the last two, not on the first one,
which is a pretty weak read because then why did the ברייתא
braisa put them all together? Okay, but anyway we do have a
fascinating ברייתא braisa. where it starts with something that sounds like a
קים ליה, Kim lei. עבודה זרה Avoda Zara and שבת, and then
it throws in a שור הנסקל. Shor Haniskal. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara to get out of the idea that there's a רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir that says you don't say קים ליה with חייב hayav
מיתה, says we're talking about a third party, טובח על ידי אחר.
toveiach al yedei acher. There's no קים ליה. Why do the רבנן
Rabbanan disagree? It could be said the רבנן Rabbanan don't buy into
this idea of טובח על ידי אחר. toveiach al yedei acher. Maybe
they think that if a third party does it, that makes you
exempt regardless of שבת. But the גמרא Gemara is now working with
the assumption that everybody says if it's done by a third party
you're liable. So the reason the רבנן Rabbanan would say here that
you are exempt, it is saying, is not about קים ליה, there's
no קים ליה, it's through a third party, it's because of שחיטה
שאינה ראויה. shechita she'eina re'uyah. The שחיטה shechita doesn't make the meat
permissible. By שבת, that's debatable whether that would apply or not, so
maybe they're not referring to the שבת case. Charlie, you had a
question from before? The גמרא Gemara. answered it. Excellent. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara. says like this. רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir אמאי מחייב
שוחט לעבודה זרה? amai mechayev shocheit l'avoda zara? Now we're going to
have fun, we're going to work through all these three cases. So
we're a little bit putting aside our problem before about יום כיפור
and קים ליה. Somehow we've answered that that's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
who doesn't say קים ליה by a case of מלקות. Now we're
going to work through the three cases: שבת, עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara,
and שור הנסקל. Shor Haniskal. So שבת we did. It's not קים
ליה because it's על ידי אחר. al yedei acher. Is it שחיטה
שאינה ראויה? shechita she'eina re'uyah? Maybe yes, maybe no, depends on רבי
יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan and סנדלר Sandler if it's דאורייתא d'oraissa or דרבנן.
d'rabbanan. Good. Now let's get to עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. That seems
to be a clear case of שחיטה שאינה ראויה, shechita she'eina re'uyah,
right? It doesn't make the meat permissible. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
I don't care, you're still חייב. chayav And the רבנן Rabbanan say
no, it doesn't make the meat permissible, you're exempt. The גמרא Gemara
says one minute, I don't understand why you would be חייב chayav
according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir even if שחיטה שאינה ראויה shechita
she'eina re'uyah is called a שחיטה. shechita. Why not? אמאי מחייב שוחט
לעבודה זרה? amai mechayev shocheit l'avoda zara? כיון דשחט ביה פורתא אסרה.
keivan d'shachat bei purta asrah. As soon as you started שחט shechting
it, you started, you made a nick in the neck of the
animal with your knife, you made it forbidden. Why? Because what makes
something forbidden to עבודה זרה? Avoda Zara? It's not a הלכה halacha
that you have to do שחיטה shechita on an animal to make
it forbidden to עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. If you bow down and
worship an animal, you make it forbidden to עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara.
The only thing is the following: is that any act of worship
to the animal or using the animal as a way of offering
it to a pagan god is an act that makes it forbidden.
The only thing is that if it's not your animal, then you
can't make somebody else's thing forbidden just because you bowed down to
it. Right? I mean, someone who's willing to do עבודה זרה, Avoda
Zara, he'd be willing to do other things. Anyway, okay, but that's
not true. It's not, you don't have a right to assign a
status, to give, change the status of something that isn't yours just
because you somehow did some thing that doesn't even affect the object
in a physical way. But as soon as you actually make, sort
of like the גמרא Gemara before about the, remember about the
גנב and the שינוי שם shinui shem and
when he trimmed it? And even if he didn't have to trim
the leather, once he was sort of taking control in that way
he was in a position to designate. So here too, if I
bow down to your animal, I don't make it forbidden. But if
I offer it to the god, if I just put it on
an altar, I actually haven't physically changed it. Okay, but if I
make a nick in it as a way of offering it up
to the god or as designating it as the object of my
worship, I would make it forbidden. Once I actually physically change it,
then I am taking enough control that my act of worshipping it
or offering it up as an offering makes is meaningful. Okay, I
have enough control that I can give it its status and therefore
I make it forbidden. So the גמרא Gemara says is look, the
שחיטה shechita that makes you חייב chayav for four and five comes
when you finish the act. Okay. The thing that makes it an
object of offering to the עבודה זרה Avoda Zara is the first
nick because then you've taken control over it. Okay, so by the
time you're done with the שחיטה shechita and you should be liable
the four and five, the object's already worthless. Right? It becomes worthless
as soon as you do the first nick, and then it's only
becomes an act of שחיטה shechita when you're done. At that stage
you're שחט shechting something that is אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. So why
should you pay the owner? The thing is worthless at that stage.
Okay, doesn't matter על ידי אחר al yedei acher or על ידי
al yedei yourself. Let's say על ידי אחר al yedei acher so
we don't have to deal with the קים ליה problem. But that's
not the focus right now, we're bracketing that. Okay, but the גמרא
Gemara: says this is worse than שחיטה שאינה ראויה. shechita she'eina re'uyah.
שחיטה שאינה ראויה shechita she'eina re'uyah until I finished the שחיטה shechita
it was totally a normal animal of the owner's. Okay, and I
was doing a שחיטה, shechita, and at the last moment when I
was חייב chayav four and five, that was maybe the moment I
turned it into, it was a טרפה treif and it became not
fit to be eaten or something like that. Or it was a
violation of שבת and became not fit to be eaten. It all
happened at the moment that the שחיטה shechita was done. So you
could say, okay, but the act of שחיטה shechita was done to
the owners. animal. Okay, but here, the act of שחיטה, shechita, the
first second, okay, it became אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. And something אסור
בהנאה, assur behana'ah, number one, is often considered in certain ways not
even belonging to the owner, and it's certainly worthless. So by the
time you finish the act, you're שוחט shechting something that's worthless and
doesn't and in some ways doesn't belong to the owner. So how
are you חייב? chayav Yes. Did you say something similar about חילול
שבת? chilul Shabbat, That the first minute is חילול שבת... chilul Shabbat
No, because the חילול שבת, the מלאכה melacha of חילול שבת is
נטילת נשמה, netilat neshama, is שחיטה. shechita. Okay? Now, you could interest...
interesting question: could you say that there's a חבלה chavala that occurs
before the שחיטה shechita is done, so maybe you could? But the
גמרא Gemara for somehow wasn't bothered with that, which is fascinating, right?
What type of a taking out of blood would be considered a
מעשה חילול שבת, ma'aseh chilul Shabbat, is it, you know, מלאכה שאינה
צריכה לגופה melacha she'eina tzricha legufa at a certain stage, but yeah,
you could ask that. Now תוספות Tosafot asks a great question. תוספות
Tosafot says, I don't get it, every שחיטה shechita is that way.
From the moment you begin שוחט shechting it, you did a שינוי
shinui and it's your animal, and then by the time you're done,
you're שוחט shocheit your animal. So תוספות Tosafot says, well, maybe it's
not a big enough שינוי shinui until you're done. Although I would
think that the better answer is like, okay, but that's like the
necessary circumstances in which the תורה Torah says you're חייב. Okay, we
have to bracket that part, the שינוי shinui part. But if there's
something else that makes it change its status before you're done, then
you shouldn't be liable at the time that you're finished. Okay, so
that's the גמרא's Gemara question. Dov, it looks like you have a
question. No? I was... it's because בהכי חייביה רחמנא be hachi chiyveih
rachamana distinction? That's a standard answer. Like, you know, you know, otherwise
you couldn't be חייב. So the תורה Torah has to have to
bracket that reality, right? But you know, but it's not bracketing all
realities. Okay. Yeah, you want it to be consistent. I hear that.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. כיון דשחיט בה פורתא
אסרה, אידך איסורי הנאה ולאו דמרא קטבח. keivan deshachit bah purta asra,
idach issurei hana'ah u'lav demara katbach. Once you finish the act, it's
already forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah, you're not שוחט something that belongs to
the owner. Okay, רש"י Rashi tells us... phrases it "it doesn't belong
to the owner", you know, רש"י Rashi tells us both also throw
in the idea that it's not worth anything. אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
says רבא, Rava, באומר בגמר זביחה הוא עובדה. be'omer begmar zvicha hu
ovda. Okay, so what you say is, I am not actually worshipping
it, if the act of שחיטה shechita is an act of worship,
which would be funny, or I'm actually not doing this as an
act of worship, an act of offering this to the god, except
with the when I finish the שחיטה. shechita. The beginning should not
be considered the act of worship, only the finish, so it all
comes at the same time. Which makes sense, right? Right, exactly. Like
even if you brought it in front of the altar, presumably the
act of worship is the slaughtering of it, not the beginning of
the process. I would agree with that. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says, שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, fine. So now we've dealt with the
עבודה זרה avodah zarah case. Let's move on to the שור הנסקל
shor haniskal case. So שור הנסקל shor haniskal says the גמרא, forget
this fancy idea of beginning of the act, end of the act.
How are you ever חייב for שור הנסקל? shor haniskal? The thing
is worthless. Why should... fine, four and five times zero is still
zero. Like, you know, and if it's איסור הנאה, issur hana'ah, then
we... you might also be the idea it doesn't belong to the
owner. How do you ever have a חיוב chiyuv for for שור
הנסקל? shor haniskal? Forget, you know, שחיטה שאינה ראויה. shechita she'eina re'uya.
So גמרא says שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, איסורי הנאה הוא. issurei hana'ah
hu. That's forbidden in benefit, ולאו דמרא קטבח. velav demara katbach. You're
slaughtering something which effectively doesn't belong to the owner. How is it
that you're paying for it? It's worth nothing. So אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, says רבא, Rava, הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha b'mai askinan, what are
you talking about? כגון שמסרו לשומר, kegon shemasro lishomer, the original owner
gave their ox, which was not yet a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal,
to a שומר. shomer. Okay, והזיק בבית שומר. vehizik beveit shomer. When
it was in the house of the שומר, shomer, it killed somebody
and it was became a שור הנסקל. shor haniskal. והועד בבית שומר,
vehu'ad beveit shomer, and it was warned in the house of the
שומר, shomer, or testified against it, not really warned because שור הנסקל's
shor haniskal the first time. ונגמר דינו בבית שומר, venigmar dino beveit
shomer, and the בית דין Beit Din פסק paskin-ed while it was
in the house of the שומר shomer that it was a שור
הנסקל. shor haniskal. Now why is all that relevant? It's still a
worthless animal. Because דרבי מאיר סבירא ליה כרבי יעקב וסבירא ליה כרבי
שמעון. de'Rabbi Meir sevira leh ke'Rabbi Yaakov usevira leh ke'Rabbi Shimon. He
holds like a רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov position and like a רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon position. Okay, not not now. What are these two
positions? סבירא ליה כרבי יעקב, Sevira leh ke'Rabbi Yaakov, he holds like
רבי יעקב, Rabbi Yaakov, דאמר אף משנגמר דינו החזירו שומר לבעלים מוחזר.
de'amar af mishenigmar dino hechziro shomer leva'alim muchzar. Even after it's been
decreed to be a שור הנסקל shor haniskal and it's worthless, the
שומר shomer can go back to the owner and say, "Oh, הרי
שלך לפניך." harei shelcha lefanecha. Here's your cow back. Okay, "Oh, too
bad it's אסור בהנאה," assur behana'ah, whatever, "but I gave you your
cow back, it looks the same." Right? That's that old question of
הרי שלך לפניך harei shelcha lefanecha that looks the same. It's sort
of like a, you know, היזק שאינו ניכר. hezek she'eino nikar. There's
nothing physical different about it. Can I say my obligation was to
give it back? I gave it back. I didn't promise it would
be worth the same amount. It's worth nothing, but I'm giving you
back the object you gave me. So we're going to start by
assuming the שומר shomer could say that. Okay? So if the שומר
shomer could say that, this object, this this ox that's אסור בהנאה
assur behana'ah is worth a lot of money to the שומר, shomer,
right? Because if the ox is alive, the שומר shomer gets off
of his $10,000 liability to the owner, he gives it back. If
it's dead, he has to pay the owner for the value of
the ox. Okay, so even though the ox is worth nothing and
nobody can derive any benefit from it, to the שומר, shomer, it's
worth its full value. All right, so we start with the idea
that the שומר shomer could give it back to the owner. Okay.
And וסברא visavara כרבי שמעון k'Rabbi Shimon and he holds like רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon דאמר דבר הגורם לממון כממון דמי, davar hagram lemamon
kemamon dami, something that would lead to a loss of money is
treated like money. Even though the שומר shomer doesn't own it and
even though it is valueless on the open market, because for the
שומר, shomer, its loss would cause a ten thousand dollar loss, it
is like the שומר's shomer ten thousand dollar object. Okay, where do
you know רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says this? דתנן, De-tnan, taught in
the משנה. Mishnah רבי שמעון אומר Rabbi Shimon omer קדשים שחייב באחריותן.
kadshei shehayav b'achrayutan. If I am liable for a sacrifice, I have
to bring a חטאת chatas and I sanctify my animal as a
חטאת. chatas. Now that animal is a חטאת; chatas; if you steal
הקדש, hekdesh, you're פטור, patur, right? וגונב מבית האיש ולא מבית הקדש.
Vegunav m'beis ha'ish v'lo m'beis hekdesh. But if you burgle it from
my house, according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, you have to pay
me כפל. kefel. Why? Because since I would have to replace it,
I'm חייב באחריות; hayav b'achrayus; I didn't just say הרי זו. harei
zo. If it's not around, I have to replace it.
Taking it from me is causing me the full loss of that
object. So even though technically it's not mine and it's הקדש, hekdesh,
and technically it's not its full value because, you know, people wouldn't
pay for it on the open market, but for me it's worth
that amount of money. So for me it's like my object that
has that value. Okay, קדשים שחייב באחריותן חייב, kadshei shehayav b'achrayutan hayav,
you're חייב. אלמא סבר Almasi דבר הגורם לממון כממון דמי. davar hagram
lemamon kemamon dami. Okay, so now we got this brilliant combination. Number
one, the שומר shomer could return the שור הנסקל shor haniskal according
to רבי יעקב. Rabbi Yaakov. And number—therefore, if you steal it from
the שומר, shomer, you have taken from the שומר shomer something that
was worth ten thousand dollars for the שומר shomer although it's אסור
בהנאה, assur b'hana'ah, it's treated like his money and like his property
worth that amount of money. And therefore, you'd have to pay him
כפל, kefel, and you'd also have to pay him even four and
five because once it started by the idea that it was considered
like his, then the שחיטה sh'chita would also make you just a
multiplier of that and make you חייב four and five as well.
And the only reason that the רבנן Rabbanan would say you're פטור
patur is because שחיטה שאינה ראויה, sh'chita she'eina ra'uya, because it's not
considered an act of שחיטה; sh'chita; an act of מכירה mechira you
would be חייב for. Okay, but that's how we get around the
problem that it's worthless and nevertheless you could be liable. So the
גמרא says, אמר רב כהנא Amar Rav Kahana אמריתה לשמעתא קמיה דרב
זביד amrisah l'shmayta kamei d'Rav Zvid מנהרדעא. mi-Nahardea. And he said wait
a minute, מי מתני מתניתין mi matnis masnisin רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
ולא רבי שמעון? v'lo Rabbi Shimon? Wait a minute, how could you
say our משנה Mishnah is like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. and not
like רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, meaning the רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. of
who says, what do you call it? The רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
who says that you would say, you know, לוקה ומשלם. We're going
back, forget, right, the ברייתא braisa we just—we had focused in on
the ברייתא. baraita But let's go back to the משנה. Mishnah The
משנה Mishnah says that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that—the משנה Mishnah.
says that if you do it on יום כיפור, you're חייב. And
the גמרא says why? Because this is the position of רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir that says that you can get lashes and still be
חייב. Okay, but one minute, והקתני סיפא, ve-ha-katani seifa, the end of
the משנה Mishnah says רבי שמעון פוטר באלו, Rabbi Shimon poter b'shelu,
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
exempts in the cases of like חולין בעזרה chullin ba-azarah and טרפה.
treifah. That's again this idea of, you know, שחיטה שאינה ראויה. sh'chita
she'eina ra'uya. Okay, so if רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is exempting at
the end of the משנה Mishnah by
שחיטה שאינה ראויה, sh'chita she'eina ra'uya, מכלל דבכולי מתניתין מודה, miklal d'bechulei
masnisin modeh, presumably he didn't have any quarrel with the first half
of the משנה. Mishnah. So again we get back to the יום
כיפור case. How can you say the יום כיפור is only a
רבי מאיר position? There's a dissenting voice at the end of the
משנה Mishnah? of רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, which sounds like the first
part of the משנה Mishnah is universally agreed upon. So how do
we—we're back to the problem, how does everybody agree to this יום
כיפור idea? So the גמרא says, אמר ליה Amar lei, רב, לא.
מכלל דמודה בטובח ומכור Miklal d'modeh b'tivcha u'machra לפלוני ולפלוני? l'fulan u'l'fulan?
No,
he's not agreed to the first half of the משנה. Mishnah. What,
you have to be discussing the whole משנה? Mishnah He's saying the
end of the משנה Mishnah talked about four scenarios: שחט shachted it
for health, שחט shachted it for dog food, שחט shachted it and
it was a טרפה, treifah, שחט shachted it and it was חולין
בעזרה. chullin ba-azarah. And רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says of those four,
I disagree with the last two. The first two you're חייב because
it can be eaten even if you're choosing to give it to
your dog, but the last two you're not חייב because it halachically
can't be eaten. But he's only discussing that last set of cases;
nobody's talking about the beginning of the משנה. Mishnah So again, how
do you explain the beginning of the משנה Mishna that for רבי—that
you are liable for שחיטה shechitah on יום כיפור? Whatever happened to
the קים ליה? And the גמרא is once again saying that is
רבי מאיר that says you can get lashes and pay. Okay, the
funny thing is that the simpler answer the גמרא could have said,
which it says in other places, is we're not talking that—we're talking
that you didn't do it במזיד or we're talking you didn't do
it with witnesses and warning, and maybe the idea of lashes is
only when the lashes are actually going to be administered. Okay, so
that would have been a different answer, but for whatever reason the
גמרא isn't going there and it's making the first part of the
משנה Mishnah רבי מאיר. And then we had this very fun exploration
of this ברייתא of שבת, עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, and שור הנסקל,
shor haniskal,
which the גמרא first said whatever happened to קים ליה and introduced
this important idea. that you're חייב for four and five even if
you do it through another person, you give it to your butcher.
So that gets out of קים ליה. The reason there that those
other things there are debated are because of שחיטה שאינה ראויה. shechita
she'eina re'uya. So first it meant saying that שבת could be a
case of שחיטה שאינה ראויה shechita she'eina re'uya because like רבי יוחנן
בן סנדרא Rabbi Yochanan ben Sandra and that could be a דאורייתא.
De'oraisa. And then it got us discussing forget שחיטה שאינה ראויה. shechita
she'eina re'uya. How are you חייב by איסורי הנאה? issurei hana'ah? It's
not worth anything. So by עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah we had a
case where you delay the status till the end, and by שור
הנסקל Shor Ha-Niskal we had this fascinating issue where it was איסורי
הנאה issurei hana'ah but for this שומר shomer that you stole it
from, it was worth money and therefore for him you, it's going
to be treated like it actually does have value. I want to
say one other point about that last thing. תוספות Tosafot asks a
question. תוספות Tosafot. says, one minute. Look at this first line of
תוספות. Tosafot וסבר לה כרבי שמעון דאמר דבר הגורם לממון כממון דמי.
Ve-savar lah ke-Rabbi Shimon de-amar davar ha-goreim le-mamon ke-mamon dami. This was
רבי מאיר. So תוספות Tosafot says תימה למה לי למימר דסבר כרבי
שמעון? Teima lama li
lemeymar de-savar ke-Rabbi Shimon? Why do I have to say רבי מאיר
holds according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon of this דבר הגורם לממון?
davar ha-goreim le-mamon? לימא דרבי מאיר לטעמיה דדן דיני דגרמי. Leima de-Rabbi
Meir le-ta'ameih de-dan dinei de-garmi. Let's say רבי מאיר goes according to
his reasoning, רבי מאיר judges cases of גרמי, garmi, וכל שכן דמחויב
בדבר הגורם לממון. ve-chol she-ken de-mechuyav be-davar ha-goreim le-mamon.
Now what's גרמי?
garmi?
You might remember גרמי garmi is, let's say I burn your IOU
document, okay, so fine, I'll pay you for the paper, but the
point is, but you, you know, you lost out hundreds of thousands
of dollars, but that was only indirect. I didn't actually destroy the
money, I just, you know, destroyed the document. Documents don't have a
market value, okay, but גרמי garmi says, look, you caused that
loss, it was pretty direct, it was technically it was a גרמא
gerama but it was very close to being a direct effect of
a loss, that's called גרמי garmi we're going to make you pay.
So תוספות Tosafot says, well isn't that the same? If you're causing
a loss you have to pay, wouldn't that be the same principle
that if I stole this thing from the שומר, shomer, I should
be חייב כפל chayav kefel to the שומר shomer because I'm causing
him this loss? How is גרמי garmi different than גורם לממון? goreim
le-mamon? They both sound the same, causing a loss of money. Okay,
but here's the answer, and תוספות Tosafot really says this answer in
the last line. Okay, but I'll say this. גרמי garmi is a
principle in the first half of בבא קמא. Bava Kamma. גרמי garmi
is a principle of מזיק. mazik. If I stole this if I
stole this cow from the שומר, shomer, maybe I would have to
pay him, I'd pay him as a מזיק, mazik, I caused him
a loss, and if it was a close enough causation, I would
pay him. But that doesn't mean I would pay him כפל. kefel.
גורם לממון Goreim le-mamon is not saying oh you caused a loss,
you caused injury, pay for the damage you caused, that's what גרמי
garmi is. גרמי garmi is a principle in מזיק. mazik. גורם לממון
Goreim le-mamon is a principle in ownership. גורם לממון Goreim le-mamon is
saying because the loss of this animal would cause you a loss
of money, it is like you own the animal, and it's like
the value of the animal is the amount
of
loss it
would cause you, you know, you would incur as a result. So
very interesting, two similar principles but have very different implications. Okay, let's
now go back to the גמרא.
גנב משל אביו וטבח ומכר. Ganav mishel aviv ve-tavach u-machar. Somebody stole
from his father and he slaughtered it and then the father died.
Okay, he's already חייב four and five, end of story. Okay, but
it's going to be contrasted in another משנה Mishnah to he stole
from his father, then the father died, so he inherited part of
it, let's say there are other brothers, he inherited part of it,
and then he slaughtered it. In that case, he didn't slaughter something
that was not totally his, it was partly his, so in that
case he's going to be פטור. patur. Okay, but if first he
slaughtered it and then the father died, he would be liable. All
right, so let's take a look at the גמרא. בעי מיניה רבא
מרב נחמן. Ba'ei mineih Rava me-Rav Nachman. Rava asked Rav Nachman: גנב
שור של שני שותפין. Ganav shor shel shenei shutafin. If somebody stole
an ox owned by two
partners, וטבחו, utvacho and he slaughtered it, והודה לאחד מהן, ve-hodah le-echad
mehen, and then he went to one of them and he admitted.
And we're assuming that if you admit to the קנס, knas, not
only do you not pay, but you get out of payment even
if witnesses show up later. Okay, so he admitted to one, so
one of them is only a half-owner, so we're assuming that that
admission gets him out. The admission is not to a court, you
could have said the admission is to a court. If you admit
to a קנס knas you're admitting to the court. Okay, but the
גמרא is assuming the admission is to the person you're liable to,
and therefore it gets you out of your liability to that person,
not to the whole liability of the case. Okay, this is an
interesting idea. Normally you think the idea מודה בקנס פטור modeh bi-knas
patur means if you admitted it in court, the court won't impose
the punishment. But here it seems like no, no, no, you admitted
it to the person you're liable to and therefore you're exempt to
that person. Okay, so you admitted it to that person, which also
raises an interesting question: where does the admission have to occur? In
court? Can the admission occur outside of court with witnesses seeing that
you admitted it and so on? Okay, so those are a lot
of interesting questions about the parameters of what type of admission exempts
you from. and therefore you're exempt to that person. Okay, so you
admitted it to that person which also raises an interesting question: where
does the admission have to occur? In court? Can the admission occur
outside of court with witnesses seeing that you admitted it and so
on? Okay, so those are a lot of interesting questions about the
parameters of what type of admission exempts you from a קנס. knas.
But we're anyway assuming that you have that scenario where you're now
exempt to that person but still liable to the other person for
his half. So he says like this: והודה לאחד מהן מהו. Vehoda
le-echad mehen mahu. What's the הלכה? halacha? Do you still have to
pay the other person five times half of the animal? חמישה בקר
אמר
רחמנא Chamisha vakar amar rachmana says five cattle and ולא חמישה חצי
בקר, velo chamisha chatzei vakar, not five half cattle, right? If you
stole a half of a cow, if you could imagine stealing half
of a cow, you wouldn't have to pay. The תורה Torah only
says you're חייב when you steal a whole cow and a whole
sheep. So maybe you only have to pay five whole cows and
five whole sheep, not five half cows. ולא חמישה חצי. Velo chamisha
chatzei. או דלמא חמישה בקר אמר רחמנא ואפילו חמישה חצי בקר. O
dilma chamisha vakar amar rachmana va-afilu chamisha chatzei bakar. No, five times
and even means
five times half of the liability. Okay, funny like, you know, where
do you begin answering this question? Like, what's in the פסוק pasuk
to tell you one way or another? So the גמרא says: אמר
ליה, Amar lei, so he said: חמישה בקר אמר רחמנא ולא חמישה
חצי בקר. Chamisha vakar amar rachmana velo chamisha chatzei bakar.
It's funny, like what's the basis of that answer? Okay, that's what
the פסוק pasuk says: five cattle only for paying five whole units,
not if you're paying five half units.
But didn't he already מודה בקנס, mode be-knas, why is our ברייתא
discussing קנס knas at all?
Because he's only—that's what I'm saying—he's only מודה בקנס mode be-knas for
half of the קנס. knas. He was מודה modeh to one
owner. He hasn't paid the other owner, right? That's the חידוש that
you don't say look, you admitted to the act, you're totally exempt.
It's seen as an admission to the party you're liable to. So
it was only an admission to somebody for half of the liability,
but he never admitted to the other half of the liability to
the person he was liable for. So that liability still exists. Okay,
but now it's going to say even if the liability still exists,
you're not going to have to pay it because the תורה only
says five full units and not five half units. Okay? So that's
his answer. איתיבי, Eisvei, so let's see if we can test this
out. גנב משל אביו וטבח ומכר ואחר כך מת אביו. Ganav mishel
aviv ve-tavach u-machar ve-achar kach mes aviv.
He stole from his father, slaughtered and then his father died. משלם
תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. Meshalem tashlumei arba-ah va-chamishah. You still have to pay.
One minute. והכא כיון דמת אביו Vehacha keivan de-mes aviv since the
father died, you now became a part owner in this cow with
your brothers. Okay, this dead cow, whatever, or any money owed to
your father, it's now partly owed to you. Okay, so if you
are one of the people this four and five is owed to,
well, you're implicitly already admitting to yourself what you did, because you
know what you did. Which is also fascinating, like I might think
admission has to come through an act of admitting. Like a lot
of times, anyway, people lie to themselves regardless, right? 'Ah, my father
owed me it, he did some bad things to me, I had
a right to...' Just because you know what you did doesn't necessarily
mean that we call it הלכתית halachically an act of admission. But
the גמרא assumes that it's like you've admitted to yourself because you
won't have to pay yourself and therefore you're only liable the remaining
80 percent to your brothers. So that's half payments, okay? כיון דמת
אביו כמי שקדם והודה לאחד מהן דמי. Keivan de-mes aviv ke-mi she-kodam
ve-hoda le-echad mehen dami. Maybe
it doesn't mean it's like you admitted. Maybe it all just means
is you're not going to pay yourself. It's not like you're admitting
and getting out of it, but in practice you're not going to
take out of one pocket and put into the other pocket. You're
not going to pay yourself for your portion, you're only going to
pay your brothers for their portions. So you're not going to pay
a full five times. You're going to pay 80 percent of five
times. You're only going to pay your brothers, you're not going to
pay yourself. ודיקתני משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. Vediktani meshalem tashlumei arba-ah va-chamishah.
So you see you can pay four and five even if you're
not paying a full four and five. So like the גמרא: כופר
ולא חצי כופר, kopher velo chatzi kopher, similar type of thing. Yeah,
you had a question? Who are you paying money to? Your brothers.
You owe—I owe the money to his father, father died, the brothers
inherited money owed to the father. Four and five, right? So each
one would get, each one would get, if there were—let's ignore the
idea of בכור. Bechor. Let's say there were two other brothers. So
they would get 66 percent of the father's money owed the father
and you would keep the other. So you're not paying the full
amount, you're only paying two-thirds of the amount, okay? And nevertheless you
pay. אמר ליה, amar lei הכא במאי עסקינן כגון שעמד אביו
בדין.
hacha be-mai askinan kegon she-amad
aviv be-din.
No, no, no. The case here is that before the father
died, there was already a court case and it was brought to
court and it was said that you have to pay four and
five. And therefore, once it was said you have to pay four
and five, then it's, then there is the payment of four and
five and any changes afterwards don't affect the idea that the חיוב
chiyuv is to pay a full four and five. Okay? So the
גמרא says one minute, right? אבל לא עמד בדין מאי? Aval lo
amad be-din mai? What would you say if there had not yet
been a court case? אינו משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה? Eino meshalem tashlumei
arba-ah va-chamishah? Then you wouldn't pay because it would not be a
full, the court would not make you liable to pay if it
were not the full payment? One minute. אי הכי דתני סיפא, I
hachi de-tani seifa, the end of the משנה Mishnah says: גנב משל
אביו ומת אחר כך טבח ומכר אינו משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. Ganav
mishel aviv u-mes achar kach tavach u-machar eino meshalem tashlumei arba-ah va-chamishah.
That when would the person be exempt? If the father died before
it was slaughtered. So according to you, that's not the point of
distinction. He doesn't have to die before it's slaughtered. He could die
later. נפלוג ודידי, Niflog ve-didei, we can make another distinction, a later
distinction. במה דברים אמורים, Bemeh devarim amurim, when is there going to
be a payment אינו משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה eino meshalem tashlumei arba'ah
vechamishah would not be because at that stage it was slaughtered but
there was no עמד בדין amad badin by the time it came
to the court you would not be fully liable because you know
now it's you and the brothers. So if that's true that you
would not be fully the court could never make you liable to
pay something that's not a full five unit it should have the
scenario that the father died after the slaughtering before the court case
and then the court would not have made you liable because you
would not be able to pay the full five units. So אמר
ליה amar lei הכא נמי hacha nami you know what you're right
it could have said that it was that the father died before
העמדה בדין ha'amadah badin but איידי דנסב רישא גנב משל אביו וטבח
ומכר ואחר כך מת אביו aidi denasav reisha ganav mishel aviv vetavach
umachar ve'achar kach meit aviv since the beginning had the case that
the father died after the slaughtering נסב סיפא נמי גנב משל אביו
ומת אביו ואחר כך טבח ומכר nasav seifa nami ganav mishel aviv
umeit aviv ve'achar kach tavach umachar that in the end it says
that the father died before the slaughtering which is not a good
answer because you know because the סיפא seifa it's like it's setting
up the case so it should have been framed as you stole
it there was העמדה בדין ha'amadah badin and then the father died
you're חייב but if the father died before העמדה בדין ha'amadah badin
you're פטור pattur why did it set it up with being about
before after the שחיטה shechitah? it should have set up being before
after העמדה בדין? ha'amadah badin? So it certainly sounds like that in
this משנה the fact that you would not pay the full four
and five is not you know not going to get you off
of paying. So that is how the גמרא concludes. גמרא says you
gotta love this twist. So in the end initially he gave these
answers but they were obviously weak answers the evidence was obviously pointing
to the idea that you would pay even if it wasn't the
full four and five. So בצפרא betzafra the next morning אמר ליה
you know what I thought about it חמישה בקר רחמנא ואפילו חמישה
חצאי בקר chamishah bakar rachamana ve'afillu chamishah chatzai bakar five even five
half half cattle okay because that fits better with the משנה because
even after the father dies you know you wouldn't be paying full
and you would still pay. אמר ליה והאי דלא אמרי לך באורתא
Amar lei vehai delo amri lach be'orta so why wasn't I thinking
about that last night? דלא אכלי בישרא Delo achli bisra because I
hadn't eaten meat. Obviously talking about slaughtering meat okay so it was
during the nine days you see that? So רש"י Rashi says it
right רש"י Rashi says it was all a metaphor. רש"י Rashi says
לא דקדקתי טעמו של דבר lo dikdakti ta'amo shel davar also טעם
ta'am if you think about it the taste anyway I wasn't thinking
so or I wasn't paying too much cognizance. תוספות Tosafot thinks he
was being literal. תוספות says שרי בתענית הוה. shari beta'anis havah. Yeah
I was fasting. What? Maybe he hadn't digested it hadn't digested it.
Anyway but you're right okay the משנה makes it clear that even
if you would be paying partial four and five you know the
the father had died and you wouldn't be paying yourself you would
still go ahead and pay four and five even if it would
not be the full four and five. But now we have one
left question left to answer then why does it matter if the
father died before the שחיטה? shechitah Even if he died before the
שחיטה shechitah? so now you're part owner with your brothers in this
cow you're שוחט a cow that's two-thirds theirs so pay them their
two-thirds. Okay but here you become an owner not you know not
before it becomes before the liability sets in. It's not just a
question of payment it's a question of liability. So that's what the
גמרא says. אלא מאי שנא רישא ומאי שנא סיפא? Ela mai shna
reisha u'mai shna seifa? What difference does it make if you become
an owner before the payment or you become an owner before the
שחיטה? shechitah Here's the difference. אמר ליה רישא קרינן ביה וטבחו כולו
באיסורא. Amar lei reisha karinan beih utvacho kulo be'issura. In the beginning
case you slaughtered it it was all not yours. It was all
the father's. So the fact that at the time of the payment
you're not going to pay full that doesn't matter. The act of
liability it was fully not yours. סיפא Seifa at the end when
the father died before the שחיטה shechitah לא קרינן ביה וטבחו כולו
באיסורא. lo karinan beih utvacho kulo be'issura. It's not being slaughtered fully
in a state of liability you have a right to slaughter a
third of it. So therefore the act has to be it's a
total act of וטבחו it's totally not your animal when you slaughter
it. But then when it comes time to pay because of admission
because of inheritance you might not pay the full amount that doesn't
matter but the liability has to be a full liability and that's
the difference whether the father died before the שחיטה shechitah. or after
the שחיטה.